Academic Relations Office fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Academic Relations Office fonds
1977 - 1995
F-203
1.63 m of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Financial assistance for the arrangement and description of the records and production of the finding aid was generously provided by Simon Fraser University's Office of the Vice-President, Academic and Provost (October 2005).
Academic Relations Office
The Academic Relations Office is the planning, policy advising and administration office for faculty, professional librarians and archivists, and academic administrators at SFU. The Office was established in 1988 with the appointment of Sharon Cochran as Director. Its main functions are to coordinate human-resources services for faculty personnel; advise faculty and provide administrative support to the appointment, renewal, tenure, promotion, and salary review processes; and liaise with the SFU Faculty Association. Prior to 1988, a number of these responsibilities had been carried out within the Office of the Vice-President, Academic (VPA) by Alison Watt in her position as the Assistant to the Vice-President (1978-1990).
Throughout its history, Academic Relations has always belonged the VPA's reporting portfolio. From its establishment in 1988 until the departure of its first Director in 1996, Academic Relations reported directly to the VPA. Subsequently, the Associate VPA, Judith Osborne, assumed direct responsibility for the unit from 1996 to 2001. A new Director, Sue Roppel, was appointed in 2001 following a reorganization of senior administrative portfolios at the university. This saw the incumbent Associate VPA (Osborne) move to the new post of Associate Vice-President, Policy, Equity and Legal, and the mandate of the Associate VPA redefined, shifting from academic employment relations to academic planning and budgeting.
published
Full
Published
The title of the fonds is based on the name of the creating body.
The fonds consists of records made or received or inherited by the Academic Relations Office in the course of its activities. Activities documented include negotiations and consultations with the SFU Faculty Association (SFUFA) relating to the collective framework agreement; development of faculty salary policy and allocation of faculty salary budgets; the activities of the Salary Equity Study Committee; administrative and record-keeping support for salary review, renewal, tenure, and promotion processes at the university. The fonds also includes a series of files inherited by the Office that were originally created by the Assistant to the VP Academic in her capacity as a university representative on the Executive Board of the SFU Childcare Society (ca. 1984-1987). Records consist predominantly of correspondence, meeting minutes and agenda, reports, and notes and working papers.
The material was arranged into series by the archivist. Based on grouping established by the creator. Files within series are arranged chronologically.
Cochran, Sharon; Office of the Vice-President, Academic and Provost
The records were transferred to the Archives in 1994 under Unscheduled Records Disposal (URD) 084-94. This transfer was part of a larger project the Archives undertook to appraise, schedule and dispose of records that had accumulated in the University Records Centre through the 1980s and early 1990s.
All accessions have been processed as of February 2006. Further accruals are expected.
A large number of the files contained in the fonds predate the formal establishment of the Academic Relations Office in 1988. In that year, the new unit assumed responsibility for a number of functions formerly handled by the Assistant to the Vice-Preisident, Academic (Alison Watt). Accordingly a substantial number of pre-1988 files originally created by Watt were inherited by the Academic Relations Office and form part of the fonds.
Records from the period in which the Associate Vice-President, Academic (AVPA) was directly responsible for the Academic Relations Office (1996-2001) were incorporated by the creator into the AVPA's record-keeping system. See fonds F-201 (Office of the Associate Vice-President, Academic), series 3-2-1, Associate Vice-President, Academic.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
A file list is available.
- General correspondence files, 1978 - 1990; F-203-1; 39 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of correspondence relating to academic personnel relations and support services. Activities and topics documented include recruitment and retirement, negotiations with the Teaching Support Staff Union (TSSU) in 1979, the provincial Compensation Stabilization Program, (1982-1984), development of the personnel payroll IT systems and the activities of the Administrative Information Systems Steering Committee (1987-1988), the employment systems review in the Office of the Vice-President, Academic (1989), and the distribution agreement with the Open Learning Agency (1989-1990). Records include correspondence, policies and procedures, reports and statistics, meeting minutes, agreements, legal advice, and notes and working papers.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist.
  Administrative Information Systems Steering Committee; Open Learning Agency; Teaching Support Staff Union
  Further accruals to the series are expected.
  Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  A file list is available.
  - Assistant to the Vice-President, Academic, vol. 1, 1978 - 1979; F-203-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 203-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Assistant to the Vice-President, Academic, vol. 2, 1978 - 1979; F-203-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 203-1)
  - Teaching workload of TA's, 1978 - 1980; F-203-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 203-1)
  - SFU-TSSU negotiations, 1979; F-203-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 203-1)
  - Compensation Stablization Program, vol. 1, 1982 - 1984; F-203-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 203-1)
  - Compensation Stablization Program, vol. 2, 1982 - 1984; F-203-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 203-1)
  - Compensation Stablization Program, vol. 3, 1982 - 1984; F-203-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 203-1)
  - Retirement, vol. 1, 1984 - 1989; F-203-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 203-1)
  - Retirement, vol. 2, 1984 - 1989; F-203-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 203-2)
  - Retirement, vol. 3, 1984 - 1989; F-203-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 203-2)
  - Employment files policy, 1985 - 1988; F-203-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 203-2)
  - General, 1986 - 1989; F-203-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 203-2)
  - Personnel / payroll system, vol. 1, 1987 - 1988; F-203-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 203-2)
  - Personnel / payroll system, vol. 2, 1987 - 1988; F-203-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 203-2)
  - Personnel / payroll system, vol. 3, 1987 - 1988; F-203-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 203-2)
  - Personnel / payroll system, vol. 4, 1987 - 1988; F-203-1-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 203-3)
  - Personnel / payroll system, vol. 5, 1987 - 1988; F-203-1-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 203-3)
  - Personnel / payroll system, vol. 6, 1987 - 1988; F-203-1-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 203-3)
  - VP Academic, 1988 - 1989; F-203-1-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 203-3)
    Creator's original file classification code: 37.1.
  - Employment systems review: VP Academic's office, vol. 1, 1989; F-203-1-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 203-3)
  - Employment systems review: VP Academic's office, vol. 2, 1989; F-203-1-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 203-3)
  - Recruitment pactices, vol. 1, 1989; F-203-1-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 203-4)
    Creator's original file classification code: 23.
  - Recruitment pactices, vol. 2, 1989; F-203-1-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 203-4)
  - SFUFA retired members, 1989; F-203-1-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 203-4)
  - [Distribution agreements], 1989 - 1990; F-203-1-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 203-4)
- SFU Faculty Association (SFUFA) consultation files, 1977 - 1988; F-203-2; 14 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the regular consultations between the university administration and the Simon Fraser University Faculty Associations (SFUFA) relating to the university policies and other matters affecting the terms and conditions of academic employment at SFU. Records include meeting agendas, minutes, correspondence, policies, notes, and working papers.
  Simon Fraser University Faculty Association
  No further accruals to the series are expected.
  - SFUFA consultations, vol. 1, 1977 - 1982; F-203-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 203-4)
  - SFUFA consultations, vol. 2, 1977 - 1982; F-203-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 203-4)
  - SFUFA consultations, vol. 3, 1977 - 1982; F-203-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 203-4)
  - SFUFA consultations, vol. 4, 1977 - 1982; F-203-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 203-4)
  - SFUFA consultations, vol. 1, 1982 - 1985; F-203-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 203-4)
  - SFUFA consultations, vol. 2, 1982 - 1985; F-203-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 203-5)
  - SFUFA consultations, 1985 - 1988; F-203-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 203-5)
  - SFUFA consultations, vol. 1, 1987 - 1988; F-203-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 203-5)
  - SFUFA consultations, vol. 2, 1987 - 1988; F-203-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 203-5)
- SFU Faculty Association (SFUFA) negotiation files, 1978 - 1990; F-203-3; 35 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to negotiations between the university and the Simon Fraser University Faculty Association (SFUFA) on matters relating to the collective framework agreement establishing the terms and conditions of academic employment at SFU. Records include correspondence, notes, policies, arbitration briefs, reports and statistics, negotiating proposals, agreements, meeting minutes, notes, and working papers.
  - Collective bargaining, 1978 - 1979; F-203-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 203-5)
  - SFUFA negotiations, vol. 1, 1980 - 1981; F-203-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 203-5)
  - SFUFA negotiations, vol. 2, 1980 - 1981; F-203-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 203-5)
  - Faculty salary arbitration, 1981; F-203-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 203-6)
  - SFUFA negotiations, vol. 1, 1981; F-203-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 203-6)
  - SFUFA negotiations, vol. 2, 1981; F-203-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 203-6)
  - SFUFA negotiations, vol. 3, 1981; F-203-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 203-6)
  - SFUFA arbitration, 1982 - 1983; F-203-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 203-6)
  - SFUFA negotiations, 1984 - 1985; F-203-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 203-6)
  - SFUFA negotiations, 1985 - 1986; F-203-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 203-6)
  - SFUFA negotiations, 1986; F-203-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 203-6)
  - SFUFA negotiations, vol. 1, 1987 - 1988; F-203-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 203-7)
  - SFUFA negotiations, vol. 2, 1987 - 1988; F-203-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 203-7)
  - Salary scales, 1987 - 1988; F-203-3-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 203-7)
  - SFUFA negotiations, vol. 1, 1988; F-203-3-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 203-7)
  - SFUFA negotiations, vol. 2, 1988; F-203-3-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 203-7)
  - SFUFA framework negotiations, 1988; F-203-3-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 203-7)
  - SFUFA negotiations, 1988 - 1989; F-203-3-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 203-7)
  - SFUFA negotiations, 1989; F-203-3-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 203-8)
  - SFUFA negotiations, vol. 1, 1990; F-203-3-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 203-8)
  - SFUFA negotiations, vol. 2, 1990; F-203-3-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 203-8)
- Faculties - correspondence, 1988 - 1995; F-203-4; 6 cm of textual records
  Series consists of the Assistant's / Director's correspondence with, related to, or copied from university faculties on matters relating to academic appointments, renewal, tenure, promotion, and sabbatical. Records consists of correspondence. For the list of faculties included in the correspondence, see "Access points" below.
  Faculty of Arts and Social Sciences; Office of the Dean of Graduate Studies; Faculty of Applied Sciences; Faculty of Science
  - Faculty of Arts - Interdisciplinary Studies, 1988; F-203-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 203-8)
    Creator's original file classification code: 11.2.a.
  - Faculty of Science, 1988 - 1990; F-203-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 203-8)
    Creator's original file classification code: 11.7.
  - Graduate Studies, 1990 - 1993; F-203-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 203-8)
    Creator's original file classification code: 11.6.
  - Faculty of Applied Sciences, 1993 - 1995; F-203-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 203-8)
    Creator's original file classification code: 11.1.
- Faculty salary budget allocation files, 1982 - 1991; F-203-5; 7 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the allocation of salary budgets to university faculties. Records include correspondence, budget requests, authorizations, budgets, notes and calculations.
  - Faculty salary budget, 1982 - 1983; F-203-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 203-8)
  - Faculty salary budget, 1983 - 1984; F-203-5-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 203-8)
  - CFL budget, 1987 - 1988; F-203-5-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 203-9)
  - CFL budget, 1988 - 1989; F-203-5-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 203-9)
  - Faculty salary budget procedures, 1991; F-203-5-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 203-9)
- Salary Equity Study Committee files, 1988 - 1991; F-203-6; 11 cm of textual records; Salary Equity Study Committee
  The Salary Equity Study Committee was established by the Vice-President, Academic in 1988 in response to concern on the part of Academic Women, the SFU Faculty Association, and the university administration about the the possible existence of gender-based salary differentials at SFU. The Committee's mandate was to determine whether gender-associated salary differentials exist among SFU's tenured and tenure-track faculty members, and if differentials exist, to recommend to the Vice-President, Academic a remedy based on the study findings. The Committee reported to the VP Academic in February 1991 with recommendations relating to methodology to determine the appropriate salary of each SFU tenure-track female faculty member relative to her peers, given academic performance; and measures to prevent future salary inequities.
  This series consists of the working files of the Director of Academic Relations who chaired the Salary Equity Study Committee. Records include meeting agendas, minutes, reports (including the Committee's final report), correspondence, statistics, notes, and working papers.
  - Salary Equity Study Committee, 1988 - 1990; F-203-6-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 203-9)
    Open
  - Salary Equity Study Committee, 1989; F-203-6-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 203-9)
    Creator's original file classification code: 30.1.
  - [Notes, working papers, drafts], 1989 - 1990; F-203-6-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 203-9)
  - [Notes, working papers, drafts], 1989 - 1990; F-203-6-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 203-9)
  - Salary Equity Study Committee, vol. 1, 1989 - 1991; F-203-6-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 203-9)
  - Salary Equity Study Committee, vol. 2, 1989 - 1991; F-203-6-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 203-10)
  - Salary Equity Study Committee, vol. 3, 1989 - 1991; F-203-6-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 203-10)
    Restricted in part
- Salary, renewal, tenure and promotion files, 1978 - 1990; F-203-7; 35 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the operation of the university's salary, renewal, tenure and promotion review processes. Activities and topics documented include development of faculty salary scales and polices, and the activities of the Faculty Salary Policy Committee (1987); the university's professional librarians' policies; renewal, tenure and promotion recommendations and the activities of the University Tenure Committee (UTC); salary reviews and appeals, and the activities of the University Salary Review Committee (1978-1983). Records include correspondence; recommendations; statistical data, including comparisons to other universities; policies, procedures and drafts; notes and working papers.
  University Tenure Committee; Faculty Salary Policy Committee; University Salary Review Committee
  - University Salary Review Committee, vol. 1, 1978 - 1983; F-203-7-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 203-10)
  - University Salary Review Committee, vol. 2, 1978 - 1983; F-203-7-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 203-10)
  - Faculty salaries, 1979; F-203-7-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 203-10)
  - Librarians - appointment and ranking, vol. 1, 1980 - 1981; F-203-7-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 203-10)
  - Librarians - appointment and ranking, vol. 2, 1980 - 1981; F-203-7-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 203-10)
  - [Salary / renewal, tenure and promotion binder], vol. 1, 1980 - 1984; F-203-7-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 203-11)
  - [Salary / renewal, tenure and promotion binder], vol. 2, 1980 - 1984; F-203-7-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 203-11)
  - Salary review, 1981; F-203-7-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 203-11)
  - University Tenure Committee, 1981 - 1983; F-203-7-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 203-11)
  - University Salary Review Committee, 1982; F-203-7-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 203-11)
  - Faculty salaries, vol. 1, 1982 - 1983; F-203-7-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 203-11)
  - Faculty salaries, vol. 2, 1982 - 1983; F-203-7-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 203-11)
  - Faculty salaries, vol. 3, 1982 - 1983; F-203-7-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 203-12)
  - Faculty salaries, 1983 - 1984; F-203-7-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 203-12)
  - Salary review and salary appeals, 1985; F-203-7-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 203-12)
  - Salary review, 1986; F-203-7-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 203-12)
  - Faculty Salary Policy Committee, 1987; F-203-7-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 203-12)
  - Management of salary review process, 1988; F-203-7-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 203-12)
  - Renewal / tenure, 1988; F-203-7-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 203-12)
  - Salary information, 1988; F-203-7-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 203-12)
  - Renewal, tenure and promotion process, 1988 - 1989; F-203-7-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 203-12)
  - Sessional lecturers, 1988 - 1989; F-203-7-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 203-12)
  - Salary anomaly review, 1988 - 1990; F-203-7-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 203-12)
  - Lab instructors salary review, 1989; F-203-7-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 203-13)
- SFU Childcare Society files, 1982 - 1987; F-203-8; 15 cm of textual records; Simon Fraser University Childcare Society
  The SFU Childcare Society presently operates eleven programs that are collectively known as the Children's Centre. The Children's Centre is an independent, legally incorporated non-profit society with registered charitable organization status. The Children's Centre provides full and part time care to approximately 240 children, ranging in age from 3 months to 12 years. Each program has its own physical space and is often referred to as a centre. A Board of Directors is composed of parent representatives, university representatives, childcare staff representatives and community representatives. The Executive Director is an ex-officio, non-voting member of the Board, hired through the University (with direction from the Society Board) to be the Coordinator for the Society and to act as a liaison between the Society and the University.
  Daycare began at SFU in 1968 when a group of parents established the Simon Fraser Co-operative Family in a student lounge. By 1973, the Family Co-op had grown into the SFU Day Care Society with three units in different locations. By 1976, there were five licensed daycare centres all incorporated under the Burnaby Mountain Day Care Society.
  In 1976 the University provided 1.2 million dollars to fund construction of a childcare complex, the first of its kind in Canada. The University also supported the appointment of a full-time director, Emily Campbell. For funding purposes, the Burnaby Mountain Day Care Society separated into five non-profit societies, which could each apply for grants. The five societies and their nine centres formed a loose federation, The Burnaby Association of University Child Care Societies, to set overall policy, coordinate activities, and exchange information. Centres remained autonomous in financing, staffing, and style of care.
  In 1981 it became evident that current levels of University funding were in jeopardy. A Task Force was struck by the University to investigate the current organization of childcare on campus. Following recommendations of that Task Force, the five individual daycare societies were reorganized in 1982 into a single non-profit society, The SFU Childcare Society, which continues today.
  The SFU Childcare Society is funded primarily through parent user fees and Board fund raising efforts. These monies are used for staff salaries and benefits, program related expenses, equipment purchase and upkeep, playgrounds, administrative costs and utilities.
  A Licensing Agreement with the University provides for repairs and maintenance service for all the major building structures, comprehensive insurance, and the salary and benefits for the Executive Director and secretarial positions.
  This series consists of files were created by the Assistant to the Vice-President, Academic (Alison Watt) in her capacity as a university representative on the Society's Executive Board between 1984-1987. Activities and topics documented include meetings of the Board, operations of the Society, and employees relations. Records include the report of the Task Force on Financial Support to the Day Care Centre (1982), correspondence, reports, meeting agendas and minutes, budget papers, job descriptions, Board membership lists, and SFU Childcare Society handbooks, brochures, newsletters, and other printed matter.
  Task Force on Financial Support of the Day Care Centre
  - Report by the Task Force on Finanical Support to the Day Care Centre, 1982; F-203-8-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 203-13)
    File reviewed for access: Nov 2021 (RD). No restricted information identified.
  - SFU Childcare Society, vol. 1, 1984 - 1985; F-203-8-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 203-13)
    Restricted in whole
    File reviewed for access: Nov 23, 2021 (RD). File includes records containing the personal information of identifiable individuals (employment history). File restricted in whole.
  - SFU Childcare Society, vol. 2, 1984 - 1985; F-203-8-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 203-13)
    File reviewed for access: Nov 24, 2021 (ML/RD). File includes documents containing the personal information of identifiable individuals: employment and educational history.
  - SFU Childcare Society, vol. 3, 1984 - 1985; F-203-8-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 203-13)